Temperance Collection, 1832-1987
Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College
Temperance collection
1832-1987
MS 440
5 boxes (2.5 linear ft.)
Sophia Smith Collection Smith College Northampton, MA
Collection encompasses a broad social movement in which American women played a prominent role. Materials include information on the Women's Christian Temperance Union; photographs; biographies and autobiographies; postcards; songbooks; and stamps. Also included are publications from various organizations.
The Temperance Collection encompasses a broad social movement in which American women played a prominent role from the early decades of the nineteenth century into the twentieth century. They participated in a variety of organizational settings on the local, state, national and international level. While the Women's Christian Temperance Union (WCTU) is generally regarded to be the leading temperance organization from its beginnings in 1873, other local and national groups were active at different points in the Prohibition movement. That diversity is evident in this collection.
While the bulk of the material comes from the late-nineteenth and early twentieth century, the Temperance Collection also contains material from as early as 1835. There is also a significant amount of material from the post-Volstead Act (the Eighteenth Amendment) period, reflecting the fight to ward off the immediate challenges to national prohibition once it became law in 1920. This struggle, much like the earlier temperance crusade, was carried out and led by women.
Numerous secondary works address the American temperance movement and the critical role played by women in that movement. See, for example, Ruth Bordin, Woman and Temperance: The Quest for Power and Liberty, 1873-1900 (Rutgers University Press, 1990) and Janet Zollinger Giele, Two Paths to Women's Equality: Temperance, Suffrage, and the Origins of Modern Feminism (Twayne, 1995).
This collection is organized into four series:
I. Organizations
II. Biographical Material and Photographs
III. Memorabilia
IV. Oversize Material
Books on Shelf
Information on Use
Terms of Access and Use
The collection is open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection.
Additions to the Collection
Periodic additions to collection are expected. Recent additions may not be reflected in the finding aid.
History of the Collection
Materials in this subject collection were either purchased or given to the Sophia Smith Collection by various donors. The collection nearly doubled in size with a significant purchase of material in 1998. Periodic additions are expected.
Search Terms
Livermore, Mary Ashton Rice, 1820-1905; Willard, Frances Elizabeth, 1839-1898; Anti-saloon League of America--History--Sources; Woman's Christian Temperance Union--History--Sources; Prohibition--United States--History--Sources; Temperance-History--Sources; Temperance--United States--Societies, etc.--History--Sources; Women social reformers--United States--History--Sources
- SERIES I. ORGANIZATIONS (1835-1933, undated), 1.5 linear ft
  Series is divided into two subseries: Woman's Christian Temperance Union (WCTU) and Other organizations such as the Anti-Saloon League and the Loyal Temperance Legion. Within the WCTU subseries can be found convention programs; addresses; local and state meeting minutes and correspondence; and a significant assortment of pamphlets. Temperance activities within the state of Maine are especially well documented.
- SERIES II. BIOGRAPHICAL MATERIALS AND PHOTOGRAPHS (1880s-1980s, undated), .5 linear ft.
  Series contains published biographical articles, autobiographical writings, and photographs of leaders of the American and international women's temperance movements, in particular the life and career of Frances Willard.
- SERIES III. MEMORABILIA (1916-40, undated), .25 linear ft.
  Series consists of an impressive array of temperance-related postcards, most from the early part of the 20th century. Also included are songbooks and stamps from 1939 commemorating the 100th anniversary of Frances Willard's birth.
- SERIES IV. OVERSIZE MATERIAL (1894-1918), .25 linear ft.
  Series has a few oversize publications from national and state temperance organizations, mostly WCTU. There are additional oversize materials in the flat files.
- SERIES I. ORGANIZATIONS (1835-1933, undated)
  - Woman's Christian Temperance Union (WCTU)
    - Annual Conventions
      - World's: programs, 1906, 1920 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      - National
        - Programs, 1878-79, 1901-19 (Box 1, Folder 2-3)
        - Annual presidential address, 1889-1915 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      - State
        - New York and Connecticut WCTU Annual Conventions, 1901, 1933, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 5)
        - Maine WCTU Annual Conventions, 1893-1916 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      - Local
        - Melrose, Mass., WCTU programs, 1886-90 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Pamphlets, publications, and speeches
      - International, 1892-1969, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
      - National, 1889-1916, undated (Box 1, Folder 9-10)
      - State, 1904-34, undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
      - The Army Canteen, 1905 (Box 2, Folder 2)
      - The Temperance Education Quarterly, 1910 (Box 2, Folder 3)
      - To the Rescue of the Temple, 1898 (Box 2, Folder 4)
      - Speech by Mrs. A. B. Satterlee, Lock Haven, PA, undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence
      - General, international, national, 1920, undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
      - Mary A. Livermore to Mrs. Burr, Melrose, MA, 1885-98 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Minutes, by-laws, and history
      - Western Washington WCTU: minutes, 1884-93 (Box 2, Folder 8)
      - Mrs. John W. Gearhart, The Beginnings of the WCTU of Western Washington, 1883-87 (1955) (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Other organizations
    - Anti-Saloon League, 1920-30, undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Loyal Temperance Legion, 1906-07, undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Ladies American Home Education Society and Temperance Union: Annals, 1852-71 (with gaps) (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Massachusetts Woman's Committee for Law Enforcement, 1926-30 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - National Temperance Society, 1895-1902, undated (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Sisterhood of Temperance Ladies in North America, Portland, Maine, undated (circa 1850s) (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - The Temperance Offering, 1853 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Temperance Working Man's Club (London): letter, 1884 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Women's National Committee for Law Enforcement, 1922-29, undated (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Women's Organization for National Prohibition, 1932 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Various state organizations, 1851-1930, undated (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Yearbooks, 1909, 1912 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Miscellaneous, 1869-1938, undated (Box 3, Folder 10-12)
    - Correspondence
      - 1910, 1926 (Box 3, Folder 13)
      - Petitions, 1835, 1918 (Box 3, Folder 14)
- SERIES II. BIOGRAPHICAL MATERIALS AND PHOTOGRAPHS (1880s-1980s, undated)
  - Thumb Nail Sketches of White Ribbon Women, edited by Clara C. Chapin 1895 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Gordon, Anna Adams: Anna Adams Gordon: A Story of Her Life, circa 1929 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Lady Henry Somerset: Lady Henry Somerset, by Helen Hood, circa 1899 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Livermore, Mary A.: Articles by and about, undated (Box 4, Folder 4-5)
  - Perkins, Sarah: Pioneer Work: Seventy Years of Temperance Work (Ohio) undated (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Stevens, Lillian M.N.: Photograph, undated (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Willard, Frances E. (Box 4)
    - General 1889-1977, undated (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Writings: How to Win and How I Learned to Ride the Bicycle 1886 and 1895 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Photographs and slides, 1880s, undated (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Miscellaneous clippings, 1950s-1980s, undated (Box 4, Folder 11)
- SERIES III. MEMORABILIA (1916-40, undated)
  - Songbooks, 1916-28, undated (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Postcards, pledge cards, and medallion, undated (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Stamps, 1939-1940, undated (Box 4, Folder 14)
- SERIES IV. OVERSIZE MATERIAL (1894-1918)
  - Newspapers and posters, 1892-1918 (Box 5)
  - Posters: "The Kaiser's Ally in America"; Scientific Temperance Instruction, Maine Ratification Campaign (2), undated (Map-case Flat File)
- BOOKS ON SHELF
  - Mary A. Livermore, The Story of My Life (1899), [MISSING 8/2015]
  - Clara C. Chapin, ed., Thumbnail Sketches of White Ribbon Women (1895)